James Redding Grist Business Records, 1780-1920
James Redding Grist Business records 1780-1920
Grist, James Redding, d. 1874
3,269 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
James Redding Grist was a merchant in Washington, N.C.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, accounts, manifests, and other papers, of James Redding Grist, his father, Allen Grist, and of other members of the family. Materials relate to the operation of a general store, trade with the West Indies, Richard Grist's export business in New Bern, N.C., J. R. Grist's turpentine business near Wilmington, N.C., and his efforts to revive his trade in naval stores after the Civil War. Includes taxation lists, ca. 1815-1816, for Beaufort Co., N.C. Correspondents include Henry Toole Clark. A bound volume (shelved and cataloged separately) contains entries relating to the operation of a North Carolina general store and an earlier similar operation in the West Indies. The first half of the volume comprises the Thomas Dickinson ledger from St. Eustatius, West Indies, 1780-1781, with entries documenting payments for rum, madeira, slave clothing, cheese, flour, twine, nails, brown sugar, needles, and other sundries. His relation, if any, to the Grists is not known. The second half of the volume comprises the ledger of Allen Grist of Washington, Beaufort County, NC, 1813-1816, with entries for food, spirits, building material, and other sundries. A few entries in each section record slave transactions: money lent for the purchase of slaves, money paid for their labor, or money received for the actual sale of slaves.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Grist, James Redding, d. 1874
Clark, Henry Toole, 1808-1874
General stores -- North Carolina -- Washington
Merchants -- North Carolina
Naval stores
New Bern (N.C.) -- Commerce
Beaufort (N.C.) -- History
North Carolina -- Commerce
North Carolina -- Commerce -- West Indies
Slave trade -- North Carolina
Taxation -- North Carolina -- Beaufort County
Turpentine industry and trade -- North Carolina
West Indies -- Commerce -- North Carolina
Grist, Allen
Grist, Richard
North Carolina -- Beaufort County -- Washington
Contents of Collection
- John Kennedy Series
  - Correspondence, 1796-1812 (Formerly John Kennedy folders) (Box 1)
  - Financial and Legal papers, 1789-1826 (5 folders) (Formerly: Kennedy, John: Bills and Accounts folders)
    - Court Documents, 1790 folder
    - Kennedy, John: Bills and Documents folders
    - Bills and Documents of John Kennedy folders
  - Tax Lists, 1784-1789 (Formerly Documents: Tax Lists folders) (Box 2)
- Correspondence Series
  Formerly Richard Grist folders. (Includes correspondence of Allen, James R., and Richard Grist.)
  - Papers, 1814-1852, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1853-1860, June, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1860-1920 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)
- Financial and Legal Papers Series
  Formerly Grist, James Redding and Richard: Bills and Documents folders)
  - Papers, 1812-1816 (Box 4)
  - List of Taxables, 1815-1816
  - Papers, 1817-1819 (Box 5)
  - List of Taxables, 1819
  - Papers, 1827-1849, (3 folders)
  - Papers, 1850-1857, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1858-1860, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Papers, 1861-1876 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - James R. Grist: Agricultural Memorandum Book, undated
  - James R. Grist: Volume of Accounts and Memoranda, 1854-1856
- Allen Grist Series
  - Account Book, 1838-1846 (Box 8)
  - Ledger, 1813-1816, F:1714
    Also includes Thomas Dickinson Ledger, 1780-1781.
  - Ledger, 1814-1825
- Richard Grist Series
  - Daybook, 1821-1824 (Box 9)
  - Daybook, 1824-1827
  - Ledger, 1818-1831 (Box 10)
  - Ledger, 1820-1826 (Box 11)